Register of the Commission for Polish Relief Records, 1939-1949
Hoover Institution Archives
- Membership File, 1939-1947. (Box 33.-41.)
  - McCormick, Chauncey. Correspondence
    - 1940
      - April-December (Folder 3)
    - 1941 (Folder 4)
  - McCracken, Henry Noble, 1940. Correspondence (Folder 5)
  - Murray, Columba
    - Cables, 1941 April - 1942 July (Folder 6)
    - Chronological record of CPR activities (Folder 7)
    - Correspondence
      - 1940 (Folder 8)
      - 1941 (Box 38.)
        - January-May (Folder 1)
        - June-August (Folder 2)
        - September-December (Folder 3)
      - 1942 (Folder 4)
      - 1943-1947 (Box 39., Folder 1)
    - Reports on trips to Poland
      - 1940 August (Folder 2)
      - 1941
        - January (Folder 3)
        - September (Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
  - Pate, Maurice
    - Cables, 1939-1941 (Folder 6)
    - Correspondence
      - 1939-1940 (Folder 7)
      - 1941 (Box 40., Folder 1)
      - 1942 (Folder 2)
      - 1943-1944 (Folder 3)
    - Letters against and for relief. Includes letters of thanks (Folder 4)
    - Report to the Polish American Council, 1941 (Folder 5)
  - Rickard, Edgar, 1940-1941 (Folder 6)
  - Satterlee, Herbert. Correspondence, 1940 (Folder 7)
  - Sawtelle, Raymond. Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Folder 8)
  - Strauss, Lewis. Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 41., Folder 1)
  - Tuck, Hallam
    - Cables, 1940 (Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1941 (Folder 3)
  - Walcott, Frederic C. Correspondence, 1940 (Folder 4)
- Shipping Records, 1939-1947. (Box 41.-47.)
  Records, bulletins, lists, protocols, distribution plans, receipts, financial documents, summaries concerning shipments of food, cloths and medications to Poland, arranged alphabetically by subject and geographic area (primarily countries)
  - General
    - General (Folder 5)
    - Agents (Folder 6)
    - Export control schedule
      - General (Folder 7)
      - Control bulletins, 1942 (incomplete) (Folder 8)
    - Export license (Folder 9)
    - Export subsidy (Folder 10)
    - Food shipments
      - General. Genoa shipments
        - General
          - SS Guilia (Folder 1)
          - SS Manhattan (Folder 2)
          - SS Washington (Folder 3)
        - Protocols
          - Lublin
            - Distribution plan (Folder 4)
            - Primary receipts (Folder 5)
            - Secondary receipts (Folder 6)
          - Radom
            - Distribution plan (Folder 7)
            - Primary receipts (Folder 8)
          - Warsaw
            - Distribution plan (Folder 9)
            - Primary receipts (Folder 10)
        - Summary of food shipments to Poland (Folder 11)
      - Oil
        - General (Folder 12)
        - Cod liver oil (Box 43.)
          - General
            - SS Canis (Folder 1)
            - SS Jalderen (Folder 2)
            - SS Vesta Herring (Folder 3)
          - Receiving warehouses
            - Krakow
              - SS Canis
                - General (Folder 4)
                - Financial documents (Folder 5)
              - SS Vesta Herring (Folder 6)
            - Warsaw
              - SS Canis (Folder 7)
              - SS Vesta Herring (Folder 8)
    - Insurance (Box 44., Folder 1)
    - International transport (Folder 2)
    - Medical shipments (Folder 3)
    - Shipping companies
      - General (Folder 4)
      - American Bureau of Shipping. Bulletins, 1940-1941 (Folder 5)
      - American Export Lines (Folder 6)
      - American Express Company (Folder 7)
      - Italian Lines (Folder 8)
      - Leggett and Company (Folder 9)
      - Moore-McCormack Lines (Folder 10)
      - Trans-Atlantic Associated Freight Conferences (Folder 11)
      - United States Lines (Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 13)
  - Bulgaria
    - General (Folder 1)
    - Receiving warehouses
      - Krakow (Folder 2)
      - Warsaw (Folder 3)
  - Lithuania
    - General
      - Letters (Folder 4)
      - Telegrams (Folder 5)
    - First shipment
      - General (Folder 6)
      - Insurance (Folder 7)
      - Receiving warehouses
        - Krakow (Folder 8)
        - Lublin (Folder 9)
        - Radom (Folder 10)
        - Warsaw (Folder 11)
      - Second shipment (Folder 46.)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Receiving warehouses
        - Krakow (Folder 2)
        - Warsaw (Folder 3)
  - Soviet Union
    - General (Folder 4)
    - Receiving warehouses
      - Krakow
        - General (Folder 5)
        - Receipts. Includes cover letters (Folder 6-7)
      - Warsaw (Box 47.)
        - General (Folder 1)
        - Protocols (Folder 2)
        - Receipts (Folder 3)
  - United States
    - Car arrivals. List (Folder 4)
    - Clothing
      - General (Folder 5)
      - SS Rex Shipment (Folder 6)
      - SS Vasaholm Shipment (Folder 7)
- Financial Records, 1939-1949. (Box 47.-53.)
  Accounts, audits, insurance documents, payments, rates, receipts and disbursements, statements, statistics, bank records, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Accounts
    - Poland
      - 1940 (Folder 8)
      - 1941-1943 (Folder 9)
    - Portugal (Lisbon) (Folder 10)
  - Audits
    - General
      - Deloitte, Plender, Griffiths and Company
        - General
          - 1940 (Folder 11)
          - 1941-1942 (Folder 12)
      - Deloitte, Plender, Griffiths and Company (Contd.)
        - Reports
          - 1941 (Folder 13)
          - 1942 (Folder 14)
        - Miscellaneous (Folder 15)
      - Haskins and Sells
    - Report, 1940 (Folder 16)
  - Insurance documents (Box 48.)
    - General, 1939-1943 (Folder 1)
    - Johnson and Higgins Marine Insurance, 1940-1943 (Folder 2)
    - Marsh and McLennan insurance (Folder 3)
  - Payments (Folder 4)
  - Rates (Folder 5)
  - Receipts and disbursements
    - General (Folder 6-7)
    - General (Box 49., Folder 1)
    - Lisbon (Folder 2)
    - Madrid (Folder 3)
  - Statements
    - General
      - General
        - 1940 (Folder 4)
        - 1941 (Folder 5)
      - Audited (Folder 6)
      - Deloitte, Plender, Griffins and Co., 1944 (Folder 7)
    - Cities (Box 50.)
      - Budapest (Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 2)
    - Local Committees
  - Statistics
    - 1939-1940 (Folder 3)
    - 1941-1942 (Folder 4)
  - Subject file (Box 51.)
    - Chase National Bank
      - General, 1939 (Folder 1)
        - Correspondence
          - 1940 (Folder 2)
          - 1941 (Folder 3)
        - Receipts and statements
          - 1940 (Folder 4)
          - 1941 (Folder 5)
        - Treasury bonds, 1942-1944 (Folder 6)
      - Paris Branch (Folder 7)
      - Deutsche Bank (Box 52.)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Pending (Folder 2)
    - Federal Reserve Bank
      - General, 1940-1942 (Folder 3)
      - Regulations (Folder 4)
    - Irving Trust Company, 1940 (Folder 5)
    - Public National Bank (Folder 6)
    - United States. Department of the Treasury. Internal Revenue Service
      - General, 1941-1948 (Folder 7)
      - Coupon interests on Treasury bonds (Box 53., Folder 1)
      - Tax exemptions, 1939-1949 (Folder 2)
- Subject File, 1939-1945. (Box 53.-68.)
  Telegrams, letters, lists, minutes of meetings, articles, bulletins, memoranda, statements, press releases, broadcasts, balance sheet of food, estimates of calories, self-sufficiency ratings, food rations, data, maps, reports, agreements, records, summaries, diets, statistics, statements, settlement documents, legal documents, registration forms, protocols, bills, records, mimeograph, printed matter, publications, textbooks, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Belgian-American Educational Foundation
    - General
      - 1940 (Folder 3)
      - 1941 (Folder 4)
    - Cables (Folder 5)
  - Belgian Relief Survey. Minutes of meetings, 1941 January 19-23 (Folder 6)
  - Czechoslovakia. Issues of News Flashes from Czechoslovakia Under Nazi Domination, New York, 1941 (Folder 7)
  - Food
    - General
      - Articles, memoranda and statements pertaining to the approaching famine in European countries. Includes press release from the Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1940 July 24 (Folder 8)
      - Balance sheet of food in continental Europe, 1941 (Folder 9)
      - Clippings (Box 54., Folder 1)
      - Estimates of foreign food supplies needed in Belgium, the Netherlands, Norway and Central Poland (estimates of the proportion of such supplies to German consumption requirements) (Folder 2)
      - Data (Folder 3)
      - European self-sufficiency ratings, 1939-1941 (Folder 4)
      - Map of food districts (Folder 5)
      - Question and answer sets (Folder 6)
      - Radio broadcasts pertaining to the Hoover's Feeding Plan
        - 1940 (Folder 7)
        - 1941 (Folder 8)
      - Report by Herman Frese, "The European Food Problem and the Hoover Proposals," 1941 (Folder 9)
      - Summary of the net trade in food stuffs and feedstuffs of 23 continental European countries (yearly averages for the 1934-1938 period) (Folder 10)
      - Trade agreement between continental European countries (Folder 11)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 12)
    - The Balkans
    - Belgium
      - General (Folder 2)
      - Chronological record of visit to Belgium of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1941 January 19-24 (Folder 3)
      - Diet of the Belgian population at the end of 1940 and forecast for 1941 by E. J. Bigwood (Folder 4)
      - Food conditions
        - Articles (Folder 5)
        - Broadcast, 1941 February (Folder 6)
        - Memorandum (Folder 7)
        - Press release, 1941 February 1. Draft (Folder 8)
        - Reports (Folder 9)
      - Food rations (Folder 10)
      - Estimate of calories in the daily food diet that can be offered to Belgian consumers out of Belgian native produce (Folder 11)
      - Printed matter (Folder 12)
    - Bread grain crops of continental Europe, 1941 (Folder 13)
    - Condensed milk and cod liver oil (Folder 14)
    - Denmark (Folder 15)
    - Diets (Folder 16)
    - Exports and imports of European countries (Folder 17)
    - Famine (Folder 18)
    - Finland (Box 56.)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Vitamins and drugs (Folder 2)
    - Flour, Dark rye (Folder 3)
    - Foodstuffs (Folder 4)
    - Food ministry (Folder 5)
    - France (Folder 6)
    - Germany
      - General (Folder 7)
      - Fat resources (Folder 8)
      - Food rations
        - General (Folder 9)
        - Changes (Folder 10)
      - Food reserves (Folder 11)
      - Self-sufficiency (Folder 12)
    - Great Britain
      - General. Bulletins from Britain, 1941 January 22. (Supplement Number 21) (Folder 13)
      - Reports
        - "Britain and the Famine Situation," n.d. (Folder 14)
        - "British Blockade Loopholes," by H. B. Frese, 1941 January 16 (Folder 15)
    - Greece (Folder 16)
    - Italy (Folder 17)
    - Netherlands (Folder 18)
    - Norway
      - General (Folder 19)
      - Relief, 1940-1941 (Folder 20)
    - Occupied countries
      - Reserves of food (Folder 21)
      - Supplies needed (Folder 22)
    - Packages (Folder 23)
    - Poland (Box 57.)
      - General. Food packages (Folder 1)
      - Central Poland (Folder 2)
      - Western Poland (Folder 3)
    - Rations of food (Folder 4)
    - Romania (Folder 5)
    - Soviet Union
      - General (Folder 6)
      - Report on factors affecting food supplies (Folder 7)
    - Spain (Folder 8)
    - Switzerland (Folder 9)
  - Hoover, Herbert. Report by William Agar, "Why Hoover Is Wrong," 1941 (Folder 10)
  - Hungary, 1940-1941 (Folder 11)
  - National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies. Statement regarding the continental food problem, 1941 February 28 (Folder 12)
  - Norway (Box 58., Folder 1)
  - Orlemanski, Stanislaw, Reverend, 1944 (Folder 2)
  - Paderewski Fund for Polish Relief
    - General (Folder 3)
    - Bulletins
      - General, 1941 January-April (#1-3) (Folder 4)
      - Campaign bulletins, 1940 April-August (#1-27) (Folder 5)
    - Clippings (Folder 6)
    - List of members (Folder 7)
    - Mimeograph. Information and instructions for the formation of Committees, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - Press releases, 1940
      - January-May (Folder 9)
      - June-December (Folder 10)
    - Printed matter (Box 59., Folder 1)
  - Paderewski Testimonial Fund
    - Bulletins, 1941 May - 1942 January (#1-5) (Folder 2)
    - List of members (Folder 3)
  - Poland
    - General
      - Publications
        - Nowy Swiat
          - 1940 (Folder 4)
          - 1941 (Folder 5)
        - PM (Folder 6)
        - Polish Rewiew (Folder 7)
      - Reports
        - General
          - 1940 (Folder 8)
          - 1941 (Folder 9)
        - CPR - Trips to Poland
          - First trip, 1940 July 4-15
            - General (Folder 10)
            - Krakow (Folder 11)
            - Warsaw (Folder 12)
          - Second trip, 1940 October 29-November 3 (Folder 13)
          - Third trip, 1941 March 16-22 (Folder 14)
      - Statistics (Folder 15)
      - Textbooks (Box 60.)
        - Kurs Jezyka Angielskiego (Folder 1)
        - Kurs Jezyka Francuskiego (Folder 2)
        - Kurs Jezyka Niemieckiego (Folder 3)
        - Kurs Jezyka Wegierskiego (Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
    - Consulates, 1939-1942
      - Chicago (Folder 6)
      - New York (Folder 7)
      - Ottawa (Folder 8)
      - Pittsburg (Folder 9)
    - Embassies
      - Great Britain (Folder 10)
      - United States
        - New York (Folder 11)
        - Washington
          - 1940 (Folder 12)
        - Washington (Box 61., Folder 1)
          - 1941
    - Gold. Case against the Romanian National Bank
      - Account (Folder 2)
      - Audit, Final (Folder 3)
      - Brief of Court of Appeals (Folder 4)
      - Correspondence
        - Federal Reserve Bank of New York (Folder 5)
        - Fidelity and Deposit Company (Folder 6)
        - Irving Trust Company (Folder 7)
        - Shattuck, Bangs and Davis Attornies (Folder 8)
      - History (Folder 9)
      - Legal decision (Folder 10)
      - Settlement documents (Folder 11)
      - Statements (Folder 12)
      - Termination papers (Folder 13)
    - Government in exile (Box 62.)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Relations with CPR (Folder 2)
    - History - Occupation, 1939-1945
      - German invasion of Poland (Folder 3)
      - Russian occupation of Poland (Folder 4)
    - Medical aid to Poland
      - General
        - 1941
          - March-September (Folder 5)
          - October-December (Folder 6)
        - 1942 (Folder 7)
        - 1943-1944 (Folder 8)
      - Insurance claim (Box 63., Folder 1)
    - Medical supplies. Includes report on distribution (Folder 2)
    - Prisoners of war (Folder 3)
    - Refugees
      - General
        - General (Folder 4)
        - Hungarian Polish Committee for Refugees (Folder 5)
        - Italy (Folder 6)
        - Outside of enemy territories (Folder 7)
        - Romania. Map of refugee relief centers (Folder 8)
      - Children (Folder 9)
    - Relief agencies. Includes registration forms (Folder 10)
  - Poland (Territory under German Occupation, 1939-1945)
    - Private welfare. "The Structure of Private Welfare," 1940. Typescript report (Folder 11)
    - Public welfare. Includes reports on Jewish welfare, 1940 (Folder 12)
  - Polish Chief Relief Committee
    - Krakow (Folder 13)
    - Lublin (Folder 14)
    - Warsaw. Includes memorandum entitled "Food in Central Poland" by H. B. Frese, 1941 March 12 (Folder 15)
  - Polish Self-Help Committee (Box 64.)
    - General (Folder 1)
    - Forms (Folder 2)
    - List of participants, 1940 (Folder 3)
    - Memorandum on the activities of the Committee in Warsaw, n.d. (Folder 4)
    - Reports on activities
      - Radom (Folder 5)
      - Warsaw
        - 1940 (Folder 6)
        - 1941 (Folder 7)
  - Polish Information Bureau
    - General (Folder 8)
    - Facts and Figures (Folder 9)
    - A News Bulletin on Eastern European Affairs, 1941 March-December (Folder 10)
  - Polish Institute of Arts and Science in America (Folder 11)
  - Polish National Council of New York
    - Correspondence
      - General. Includes some documents relating to the PNC of America
        - 1940 (Folder 12)
        - 1941 (Folder 13)
      - Clothing (Box 65., Folder 1-7)
  - Polish Red Cross
    - General (Folder 8)
    - Protocols (Folder 9)
    - Statistics on stocks in warehouse (Folder 10)
  - Polish Relief Council in Warsaw
    - General (Folder 11)
    - List of members and main officers (Folder 12)
  - Rada Polonii Amerykanska (Polish-American Council)
    - Bulletins
      - 1940 (Folder 13)
      - 1941 (Box 66., Folder 1)
    - Reports, 1941 (Folder 2)
  - Romania, 1940-1941 (Folder 3)
  - Secours d'Hiver (Folder 4)
  - Slavic countries. Issues of Slavonic Bulletin, New York, 1941 (Folder 5)
  - Soviet Union (Folder 6)
  - Spat, Emil - Jewelry (Folder 7)
  - Stanford Food Research Institute
    - Memoranda and reports (Folder 8)
    - Printed matter
      - General (Folder 9)
      - Publications pertaining to the food situation
        - General (Folder 10)
        - Wheat Studies, 1939-1941 (Folder 11)
  - United States. Congress (Box 67.)
    - Congressional bills regarding financial relief to Poland and other countries (Folder 1)
    - Congressional matters, 1940 (Folder 2)
    - Excerpts from Congressional Record on food situation in Europe (Folder 3)
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - Foreign Correspondence
      - 1940 (Folder 4)
      - 1941 (Folder 5)
    - Jewish Telegraphic Agency Bulletins, 1940
      - January-February (Folder 6)
      - March (Folder 7)
      - April (Box 68., Folder 1)
      - May (Folder 2)
      - June (Folder 3)
      - July (Folder 4)
      - August (Folder 5)
      - September-December (Folder 6)
    - Overseas News Agency, New York, 1940 (Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1940-1941. (Box 69.-70.)
  383 prints and 19 negatives taken by CPR representatives, arranged by subject
  - General
    - 45 prints depicting CPR representatives Arthur Gamble and Columba Murray, Jr., during their first inspection trip to Poland (Garwolin, Krakow, Lublin, Radom, and Warsaw), 1940 July 6-12, accompanied by members of the American Joint Distribution Committee, the Central Relief Committee for Occupied-Poland, Polish Red Cross, Polish Self-Help Committee; local relief committee officials; German Red Cross representatives and other German officials; Catholic priests; Jewish Self-Help Committee, Jewish Senior Committee, Jewish Gemeinde and Judischer Ober Altestenrat representatives. Includes description of photographs (Folder A-C)
    - 3 prints depicting CPR representatives Arthur Gamble, John Hartigan, and Columba Murray giving an interview to the National Broadcasting Company, 1940 August (Folder D)
    - 25 prints depicting CPR representatives John Hartigan and Columba Murray, Jr., on their second inspection trip to Krakow and Warsaw, 1940 October 29-November 4, accompanied by members of the Polish Chief Committee, Polish Self-Help Committee, Rada Glowna Opiekuncza, St. Vincent de Paul Society; Jewish Gemeinde officials; representatives of the German Red Cross and other German officials. Includes description of photographs (Folder E-F)
    - 48 prints depicting Wm. C. McDonald on the third CPR inspection trip to Poland, 1941 March-April. Group includes members of Polish Central Relief Committee, Polish Self-Help Committee, Polish Chief Relief Committee and other Polish and German officials. Includes description of photographs (Folder G-H)
    - 29 prints depicting CPR representative Columba Murray and M. C. Lehman of the American Mennonite Committee, and scenes of relief activity in various places in Warsaw, 1941 September 25-30. Group includes Polish and German officials. Includes description of photographs (Folder I)
    - 84 prints taken by the Polish Chief Relief Committee and Self-Help Committee, depicting the distribution of relief supplies in Poland received from CPR (Folder J-N)
    - 1 print depicting Colonel William J. Donovan, President of the Paderewski Fund for Polish Relief, and Mrs. Lawrence Tibbett, Assistant General Chairman of the New York Campaign (Folder O)
  - Polish provincial cities
    - Biala Podlaska, 2 prints (Folder P)
    - Chelm, 1 print (Folder Q)
    - Hrubieszow, 1 print (Folder R)
    - Jaroslaw, 6 prints (Folder S)
    - Konskie, 2 prints (Folder T)
    - Lublin, 17 prints (Folder U)
    - Okocim Gorny, 3 prints (Box 70., Folder V)
    - Ostrowiec, 6 prints (Folder W)
    - Ostrow Mazowiecki, 2 prints (Folder X)
    - Piotrkow, 19 prints (Folder Y)
    - Przeworsk, 1 print (Folder Z)
    - Siedlce, 1 print (Folder AA)
    - Siedlce, 1 print (Folder AA)
    - Skierniewice, 3 prints (Folder AB)
    - Starachowice, 2 prints (Folder AC)
    - Zakopane, 1 print (Folder AD)
    - Zamosc, 3 prints (Folder AE)
  - Polish refugees
    - 7 prints depicting Polish soldiers arriving in Budapest (Folder AF)
    - 15 prints depicting the Bucharest Branch of the Commission for Polish Relief (Folder AG)
    - 1 print depicting the Health Unit in Pernio, Finland (Folder AH)
    - 4 prints depicting Polish refugees in Portugal (Folder AI)
    - 5 prints depicting refugees in Vilna (Folder AJ)
  - Warsaw Ghetto, 16 prints (Folder AK)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder AL)
  - Negatives
    - 12 negatives depicting the Warsaw Ghetto (Folder AM)
    - 7 negatives (4 plates) depicting the Jewish Isolation Center in the city of Radom (Folder AN)
    - 1 album of 30 prints depicting the city of Lublin (Folder AO)